Gerrit Smith Miller Papers
Gerrit Smith Miller Papers
1869-1913
Miller, Gerrit Smith, 1845-1937.
21 linear ft.
New York politician and dairy farmer; grandson of New York reformer, philanthropist and abolitionist Gerrit Smith. Collection contains correspondence, financial material, dairy business and herd records, miscellany.
2751611
Biographical History
Gerrit Smith Miller (1845-1937) was a New York politician and dairy farmer. His father was Charles D. Miller (1818-1896); through his mother Elizabeth Smith (1822-1911) he was the grandson of New York reformer, philanthropist and abolitionist Gerrit Smith.
Gerrit Smith Miller was one of the early importers of Holsteins from Holland (following the example of a neighbor, Winthrop W. Chenery) and maintained the oldest purebred Holstein herd in the United States from 1869 to 1937. Many of the 1.8 million animals registered in the Holstein-Freisian book today descend from Miller's Kriemhild herd. He was also one of the first to approach dairy farming scientifically, keep daily year-round records of milk production in his effort to increase yields. Miller was also a member of the New York State legislature, and was involved with the George Junior Republic, a boys' school founded by American philanthropist William Reuben George in 1909.
He and his wife, Susan Hunt Dixwell, had three sons: Gerrit Smith Jr. (1869- ?), Basil Dixwell (1873- ?) and William Fitzhugh (1878-1890).
A genealogy of the Smith family is available in PDF (if online) or at the end of this finding aid (if in hard copy).
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Gerrit Smith Miller Papers contains correspondence, financial material, dairy business and herd records, and miscellany.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically. Financial material is subdivided by type and within that arranged chronologically. The remaining series are arranged alphabetically by topic or type.
Related Material
has the papers of several members of the Smith family. See also the following:
Gerrit Smith Papers
Greene Smith Papers
Peter Smith Papers
Subject and Genre Headings
New York State; Politics, government and public administration; Smith, Gerrit, 1797-1874.; Smith, Greene, 1841-1880.; Smith, Peter, 1768-1837.; Miller, Elizabeth Smith, 1822-1911.; Miller, Gerrit S. (Gerrit Smith), 1869-1956.; Dixwell family.; Fitzhugh family.; Miller family.; Smith family.; Dairy farming -- New York (State); Dairy farmers -- New York (State); Legislators -- New York (State); Correspondence.; Receipts (financial records); Dairy farmers.; Legislators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - General (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - General, 1869-1878 (Jul); 32 folders (Box 1)
  - General, 1878 (Aug)-1881 (Dec); 37 folders (Box 2)
  - General, 1882-1883; 24 folders (Box 3)
  - General, 1884-1885 (Jun); 13 folders (Box 4)
  - General, 1886 (Jul)-1887 (Mar); 17 folders (Box 5)
  - General, 1887 (Apr)-1888 (Jun)\; 15 folders (Box 6)
  - General, 1888 (Jul)-1889 (Jun); 12 folders (Box 7)
  - General, 1889 (Jul)-1890 (Jun); 13 folders (Box 8)
  - General, 1890 (Jul)-1891 (Jun); 12 folders (Box 9)
  - General, 1892 (Jul)-1893 (Dec); 12 folders (Box 10)
  - General, 1894-1909; 8 folders (Box 11)
  - General, undated; 2 folders (Box 11)
- Family correspondence
  - Alerdice, Winslow (Box 11)
  - Andrews (Box 11)
  - Andrews, Ann (Box 11)
  - Berry (Box 11)
  - Biddle (Box 11)
  - Bowditch (Box 11)
  - Bowditch, Charles P. (Box 11)
  - Bowditch, Edward ("Ned") (Box 11)
  - Brent (Box 11)
  - Burns (Box 11)
  - Cochrane (Box 11)
  - Cochrane, John (Box 11)
  - Cochrane, Walter (Box 11)
  - Dixwell (Box 11)
  - Dixwell, S. (Box 11)
  - Dixwell, John ("John D.") (Box 11)
  - Dixwell, Mary T. B. (Box 11)
  - Fitzhugh (Box 11)
  - Fitzhugh, Bess V. (Box 11)
  - Forbes, Gerrit (Box 11)
  - Haines, W. K. (Basil's teacher, to GSM) (Box 12)
  - Haines, W. K. (Basil's teacher, to Basil) (Box 12)
  - Holmes, Fanny (Box 12)
  - Holmes, Oliver Wendell Jr., 1913 (Box 12)
  - Howe, Archibald (Box 12)
  - Howe, Arria S. D. (Box 12)
  - Kemeys (Box 12)
  - Kennedy (Box 12)
  - Locke, C. S. (Basil's teacher) (Box 12)
  - Lovett, James DeWolf (Box 12)
  - Miller (Box 12)
  - Miller, Mrs. (either Elizabeth Smith Miller or Susan Dixwell Miller) (Box 12)
  - Miller, Anne F. ("Nan"), 1882-1901; undated; 3 folders (Box 12)
  - Miller, Basil D. (Box 12)
  - Miller, Blandrina D. (Box 12)
  - Miller, Charles Dudley, 1876-1894; 3 folders (Box 12)
  - Miller, Charles Dudley, 1875-1895; papers (Box 12)
  - Miller, Dudley, 1875-1890; 6 folders (Box 12)
  - Miller, Dudley, papers (Box 12)
  - Miller, Elizabeth Smith, 1875-1893; undated; 8 folders (Box 13)
  - Miller, Elizabeth Smith, 1878-1910; undated; papers; 8 folders (Box 13)
  - Miller, Esther (Box 13)
  - Miller, Gerrit Smith Jr., 1888-1889; 3 folders (Box 13)
  - Miller, Louise (Box 13)
  - Miller, Mary S. (Box 13)
  - Miller, Susan Dixwell ("Susansy", 1876-1889; undated; 4 folders (Box 14)
  - Miller, Susan Dixwell ("Mother Miller" and "Sister Bee"), 1880-1912; undated; papers; 4 folders (Box 14)
  - Miller, Susan Dixwell, letters from her mother-in-law, Elizabeth S. Miller (Box 14)
  - Miller, Susan Dixwell, letters from her brother-in-law, Dudley Miller (Box 14)
  - Miller, William Fitzhugh (Box 14)
  - Miller, William Fitzhugh and others (Box 14)
  - Owen (Box 14)
  - Owen, Arria D. (Box 14)
  - Price (Box 14)
  - Savage (Box 14)
  - Smith, Ann C. (Box 14)
  - Smith, Elizabeth ("Bessie" or "Betsey"), 1875-1901; undated; wife of Greene Smith; 4 folders (Box 14)
  - Smith, Gerrit (Box 14)
  - Smith, Gerrit H. (Box 14)
  - Smith, Greene, 1875-1876; 4 folders (Box 14)
  - Smith, Greene, 1877-1880; 3 folders (Box 15)
  - T—, Rebecca F. (Box 15)
  - Walter, Ellen (Box 15)
  - Watson (Box 15)
  - Watson, C., 1881-1896; 7 folders (Box 15)
  - —, Katy (Box 15)
  - —, Mary (sister) (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous and unidentified family letters and fragments, 2 folders (Box 15)
- Business correspondence
  - 1861-1876, 8 folders (Box 15)
  - 1877-1889, undated, 15 folders (Box 16)
  - 1875-1911, undated, 6 folders (Box 17)
- Financial material
  - Unsorted financial records (Box 18)
  - Cancelled checks (Box 19)
- Business records
  - Unsorted business records (Box 20)
  - Unsorted dairy herd materials (Box 21)
  - Unsorted business records (Box 22)
- Memorabilia
  - Business card (Box 23)
  - Photographs (Box 23)